"Are the Benefits of Cold Plunges
and Cryotherapy Just a Placebo Effect?"
Cold-water immersion
is a post-exercise modality
purported to enhance
physical recovery
following strenuous exercise,
and people certainly report
feeling less sore,
less fatigued,
and more recovered
after cold plunging,
but the vast majority
of cryotherapy studies
have been conducted using
a do-nothing control group,
like just sitting in a chair,
and have not taken
expectancy effect
or treatment belief
into account,
meaning maybe the cold plunge
only works
because people think it works.
In other words, could it
just be the placebo effect?
Practitioners didn’t
just feel better, though;
in some cases,
they performed better too,
but that also could be
a placebo effect.
Give athletes placebos,
and there aren’t only effects
on perceived exertion,
for example,
but on actual muscle power,
running speed,
and even heart rate.
Placebos, like sugar pills,
that are deceptively claimed
to be some
performance-enhancing drug,
actually enhance performance.
Or, give one set of people
a capsule of corn starch
and say it’s going
to make them run faster,
and another the same capsule
and tell them it’s going
to make them run slower,
and, you guessed it,
the it-will-make-you-faster
group ran faster,
and the it-will-make-you-slower
group ran slower.
Give people a sugar pill
and tell them
it’s a strong combination
of amino acids
with immediate effects
on strength,
and they magically leg
and bench press more,
until they’re informed
they were lied to
and learn
it was just a sugar pill,
and just like that,
their performance enhancement
disappeared.
You can even get
a dose-response effect.
When people were told
they were getting
about 300 mg of caffeine,
600 mg of caffeine,
or a placebo,
even though
everybody got placebos,
the ones who were told
they got the placebo did worse,
and there was increased power
in the lower
fake-caffeine group,
and even more in the higher
with all the fake-caffeinated
participants
even reporting
caffeine-related side effects.
Once people are told
they are taking a substance
that will enhance performance,
all sorts of things kick in:
belief, pain sensation,
expectancy, and arousal,
all of which
may impact performance.
No wonder there’s a gazillion
dollar sports supplement market
selling tons of drinks,
powders, and supplements.
They may work, but maybe not
any better than a sugar pill,
which would certainly be
a lot cheaper.
For cold-water immersion,
it’s difficult to administer
a true placebo,
but researchers cited a study
that did include
a placebo treatment,
and the effect
of cold-water immersion
was found to be no bigger
than the placebo effect.
There have actually been
five such studies to date.
Here’s the one
they were referring to.
Thirty guys performed
an acute high-intensity
interval training session,
comprised of four
30-second sprints,
immediately followed
by one of the following
three 15-minute
recovery conditions:
cold-water immersion
at 10.3°C +/- 0.2°C,
about 50°F,
a warm, near-body temperature
water immersion placebo,
or a warm, near-body temperature
water-immersion control group.
Uh, hold on.
What’s the difference
between the placebo group
and the control group?
In the placebo group,
the researchers squirted
something in the water
(actually just some soap)
and led the participants
to believe it had special
recovery enhancement properties.
Here’s how everyone did
in terms of recovery
of muscle strength
measuring maximal voluntary
isometric contraction strength,
both peak and average.
Here’s how the cold-water
immersion did,
and here’s how
the warm immersion
with the fake
ergogenic soap did,
significantly better than just
the plain warm-water group.
This study demonstrated
that influencing one’s belief
in the efficacy
of warm-water immersion
as an ergogenic aid
in recovery
can account for an approximate
13 percent improvement
in muscle strength 48 hours
after high-intensity exercise;
so, it’s important for coaches
and sports scientists alike
to educate their athletes
on the benefits of recovery
and to also encourage belief
in the practice.
Wait, are they encouraging them
to lie to athletes?
Hey, if that lie is going
to increase performance
by 13 percent.
Here are the other four
placebo-controlled
cold-plunge studies.
Cold-water immersion offers
no functional or even
perceptual benefit
compared to a sham intervention
during an eight-week
resistance training program.
Here, researchers told people
in the control group
that their protein supplements
were tweaked
and that was enough
to completely eliminate
any significant effect,
and had the training program
gone longer,
they would expect
the cold-immersion group
to actually shrink
long-term gains in muscle mass,
or strength, or both.
The next was cold-water
immersion after a soccer match,
randomized to cold plunge,
passive rest recovery,
or a quote-unquote
"recovery" beverage,
which was just a placebo.
And both the cold plunge
and placebo were more effective
than the rest condition.
Doing something made people feel
better than doing nothing,
but the cold plunge did no
better than the fake beverage,
demonstrating that indeed
cold-water immersion reduces
muscle soreness,
but this beneficial effect
was a manifestation
of the placebo effect.
What about whole-body
cryotherapy--
like sitting in a cryochamber
at 100 below zero F (-73°C)--
versus cold plunge or placebo
after resistance exercise?
Neither cryotherapy intervention
was more effective
than the placebo treatment
at accelerating recovery,
neither was more effective
as a pill of cornstarch,
as long as you tell people
that cornstarch pill
is a branched-chain
amino acid supplement.
Oh my God, are athletes
that gullible?
No wonder these supplement
companies make off like bandits.
The majority of group
comparisons revealed
unclear, trivial, or unfavorable
effects of cryotherapy
compared to the placebo
intervention,
meaning in some ways,
the magical cornstarch pill
worked better,
contradicting much
of the previous literature,
but that’s because
much of the previous literature
compared cold-water immersion
to nothing,
just like sitting in a chair.
And finally,
recovery following a marathon:
a comparison
of cold-water immersion,
whole-body cryotherapy,
and a placebo control group
given a fake tart cherry
juice beverage.
Neither cold treatment,
whether wet or dry,
was more effective
than a placebo
at improving
functional recovery
or even perceptions of training
stress following a marathon.
In fact, the placebo worked
even better.
Cold water worked better
than the cryotherapy,
but they both did worse than
the fake fruit-flavored drink.
These findings lend
further evidence to suggest
that treatment belief
and the placebo effect
may be largely responsible
for the beneficial effects
of cryotherapy on recovery.
But what about the objective
drop in muscle damage indicators
after cold-water immersion?
It’s been reasoned
that reducing
muscle temperature
and blood flow
may dampen the local
inflammatory response
and thereby boost
post-exercise recovery.
What is striking is the
assumption that inflammation
needs to be dampened
or suppressed.
Isn’t inflammation
a crucial component
of the adaptive response
of skeletal muscle to training?
And cold plunges aren’t
actually anti-inflammatory.
Where did we even get
that idea from?
It was from studies
on lab animals
with induced
gross muscle injuries,
which isn’t exactly the same
as just exercising strenuously.
Okay, but there’s still
that reduced muscle damage,
even if doesn’t affect
inflammation
or muscle function recovery.
But doesn’t exercise-induced
muscle damage play a role
in skeletal muscle growth?
Might dampening the damage
be throwing cold water
on muscle growth?
We’ll find out next.